<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Gina Schmalzle</title><link href="http://ginaschmalzle.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://ginaschmalzle.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://ginaschmalzle.github.io/</id><updated>2014-03-19T14:56:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Projecting GPS velocity vectors onto a profile</title><link href="http://ginaschmalzle.github.io/VectorProj.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-19T14:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Gina Schmalzle</name></author><id>tag:ginaschmalzle.github.io,2014-03-19:VectorProj.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="section" id="global-positioning-systems"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Positioning Systems&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Positioning Systems&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;GPS&lt;/strong&gt;) are used to measure the three dimensional position of a point over time. High precision GPS are used to measure tectonic plate motion by measuring the position of a permanently installed geodetic monument over time.  The GPS instruments are either permanently installed over the monument and continuously recording its position over time, or the GPS monuments are perodically measured. With either method, three dimensional position estimates are made over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an image of a high precision GPS antenna, whose image I took from the UNAVCO website:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="UNAVCO GPS antenna" class="align-right" src="http://facility.unavco.org/project_support/engineer-equip/images/1ASHM_north_stripped2.jpg" style="width: 200.0px; height: 200.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is an example of the GPS site BEMT position 3D time series taken from UNAVCO:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="UNAVCO GPS antenna" class="align-right" src="http://cws.unavco.org:8080/cws/modules/GPStimeseriesCA/versions/version2011may/BEMT_2011.png" style="width: 400.0px; height: 400.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue dots are daily position estimates in the north (top), east (middle) and vertical (bottom) components.  This site experienced an offset due to an earthquake in 2010.  For more information on how GPS works, please visit:  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unavco.org/edu_outreach/teachers/teachers.html"&gt;http://www.unavco.org/edu_outreach/teachers/teachers.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="gps-velocities"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GPS Velocities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rate at which a geodetic monument moves can be estimated by taking the slope of the time series for each component.  Take for example the time series shown above.  This is going to be a rough estimate, but between 2004 and 2010, the monument north component position moved from -15 mm to +15 mm, totalling 30 mm of displacement over 6 yrs, indicating that it is moving at 5 mm/yr in the north position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="North Component" class="align-right" src="/images/NGPS.png" style="width: 200.0px; height: 200.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the same logic, the east component moved ~-50 mm over about 6 years, giving the east component a rate of 8.3 mm/yr to the west.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="East Component" class="align-right" src="/images/EGPS.png" style="width: 200.0px; height: 200.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Magnitude and direction of the horizontal GPS velocity vector can now be calculated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Horizontal Components" class="align-right" src="/images/ENGPS.png" style="width: 400.0px; height: 400.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="vector-projection"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vector Projection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In map view small variations in GPS velocities may be difficult to see, hence it is sometimes useful to plot GPS velocities along a profile. The profile line can follow a fault line, and, if it does, one can calculate the fault parallel and perpendicular components of motion.  Fault parallel motion will give you an idea of lateral motion across the fault (as in strike-slip fault systems), and fault perpendicular motion will tell you if the two sides of the fault are separating or converging.  In this section, we will talk about deriving the profile parallel and perpendicular components of the GPS vectors using &lt;strong&gt;vector projection&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Horizontal Components" class="align-right" src="/images/vector_projection.png" style="width: 400.0px; height: 200.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the fault perpendicular velocity is: R perp= R*sin(t)
and the fault parallel velocity is: R par= R*cos(t)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-vector-projector"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Vector Projector&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stuart Sandine&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Andrea Fey&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Thomas Ballinger&lt;/strong&gt; and I created a web app called &lt;strong&gt;The Vector Projector&lt;/strong&gt; that calculates the magnitude, transect parallel and transect perpendicular components of GPS velocities along a profile.  In this app, you are given the option of several GPS velocity fields, calculated with respect to stable North America.  For now you can choose your profile width and you can filter what data you would like to use by their uncertainties (i.e., uncertainties that are more than the value specified are not used).  This beta version does not plot uncertainties, which we plan to change in the future.  Give it a try! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://geodesygina.com/vectorprojector/vectorprojector.html"&gt;Go to the Vector Projector&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="GPS"></category><category term="vector projection"></category></entry><entry><title>About Me</title><link href="http://ginaschmalzle.github.io/MyBio.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-13T12:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Gina Schmalzle</name></author><id>tag:ginaschmalzle.github.io,2014-03-13:MyBio.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;img alt="Gina Schmalzle" class="align-right" src="/images/Gina.jpg" style="width: 200.0px; height: 200.0px;" /&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="hello-i-m-gina"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hello! I'm Gina.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a geodesist who recieved her PhD at the University of Miami Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Sciences in Miami FL.  Since then I have been a postdoctoral scholar and research scientist at the University of Washington in Seattle, WA, and along with Scott Baker and Batuhan Osmanoglu, started a geodetic services company called BOS Technologies, LLC (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bostechnologies.com/"&gt;http://bostechnologies.com/&lt;/a&gt;). We specialize in high precision Global Positioning Systems (GPS) and Interferometric Synthetic Aperture Radar (InSAR).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently attending Hacker School (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.hackerschool.com/"&gt;https://www.hackerschool.com/&lt;/a&gt;) in downtown Manhattan, NYC, where I am working on developing interactive websites for geophysical datasets.  Many geophysical datasets are publicly available, but it is difficult for the general public to use and play with these data.  One of my goals here at Hacker School is to develop web based tools that allow users to explore these fascinating datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="Gina"></category><category term="Schmalzle"></category><category term="BOS Techonologies"></category><category term="Hacker School"></category></entry><entry><title>Setting up Custom Domain Names with Github Pages</title><link href="http://ginaschmalzle.github.io/GeodesyGina.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-11T13:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Gina Schmalzle</name></author><id>tag:ginaschmalzle.github.io,2014-03-11:GeodesyGina.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello World!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my first blog post generated by pelican and hosted by &lt;strong&gt;github&lt;/strong&gt; with my snazzy new domain name &lt;strong&gt;geodesygina.com&lt;/strong&gt;!  That is pronounced:
GEE-ODD-ESS-Y-GEE-NA.  Ha! I'm such a geek.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, thanks to Amy Hanlon who posted directions on how to set up a blog with &lt;strong&gt;Pelican&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mathamy.com/"&gt;http://mathamy.com/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I purchased  my &lt;strong&gt;domain name&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;strong&gt;geodesygina.com&lt;/strong&gt;) with &lt;strong&gt;godaddy.com&lt;/strong&gt;, for $12.19 for 2 years.  Getting the &lt;strong&gt;domain name&lt;/strong&gt; to point to &lt;strong&gt;github&lt;/strong&gt; was a little tricky.  &lt;strong&gt;Github&lt;/strong&gt; posted a &amp;quot;Setting up a custom domain with Pages&amp;quot; site (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-a-custom-domain-with-pages"&gt;https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-a-custom-domain-with-pages&lt;/a&gt;) that goes through how to set up your &lt;strong&gt;domain name&lt;/strong&gt; in your repository.  This part is pretty clear until you need to set up your DNS.  I can only speak for my experience at godaddy.com, but this is how you set up your DNS through them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log into your godaddy account.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the My Account page and click on the green launch button to the right of where it says domains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On the Domains page, click on the domain name. On the page it brings you to click the tab that says DNS Zone File then click edit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the A(host) section. There should be 1 record with &amp;#64; as the host. Github has two different IP addresses. Edit the current one. Keep the &amp;#64; as the host and replace the IP address with 192.30.252.153. Once that is in, click &amp;quot;Quick add&amp;quot; right underneath and for the new record, put &amp;#64; as the host again and enter the IP address 192.30.252.154.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That should be it! It may take a little time for your website to update.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="pelican"></category><category term="custom domain name"></category><category term="godaddy"></category></entry><entry><title>My Publications</title><link href="http://ginaschmalzle.github.io/MyPubs.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-10T02:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Gina Schmalzle</name></author><id>tag:ginaschmalzle.github.io,2014-03-10:MyPubs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Schmalzle, G., McCaffrey, R., Creager, K., Central Cascadia Subduction Zone Creep, Geophysics, Geochemistry, Geosystems, doi: 10.1002/2013GC005172, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karimzadeh, S., Cakir, Z., Osmanoglu, B., Schmalzle, G. M., Miyajima, M., Amiraslanzadeh, R., and Djamour, Y., Interseismic strain accumulation across the North Tabriz Fault (NW Iran) deduced from InSAR time series, Journal of Geodynamics, 66, doi: 10.1016/j.jog2013.02.003, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gourmelen, N., Dixon, T.H., Amelung, F., Schmalzle, G. M., Acceleration and Evolution of Faults: An Example from the Hunter Mountain-Panamint Valley Fault Zone, Eastern California, Earth and Planetary Science Letters, 10.1016/j.epsl.2010.11.016, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fulton, P., Schmalzle, G. M., Harris, R., Dixon, T. H., Reconciling patterns of interseismic strain accumulation with thermal observations across the Carrizo segment of the San Andreas Fault, Earth and Planetary Science Letters, 10.1016/j.epsl.2010.10.024, 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schmalzle, G. M., The Earthquake Cycle of Strike-Slip Faults, PhD Thesis, University of Miami, Miami, FL, 211 pp., 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Biggs, J., Burgmann, R., Freymueller, J., Lu, Z., Parsons, B., Ryder, I., Schmalzle, G. M., Wright, T., The postseismic response to the 2002 M7.9 Denali Fault earthquake: constraints from InSAR, Geophysical Journal International, 175 (3), 10.1111/j.1365-246X.2008.03932.x, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schmalzle, G. M., Dixon, T.H., Malservisi, R., Govers, R., Strain accumulation across the Carrizo segment of the San Andreas Fault, California:  Impact of laterally varying crustal properties, Journal of Geophysical Research, B, Solid Earth and Planets, 111, doi:10.1029/2005JB003843, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sabburg, J., Kimlin, M. G., Rives, J. E., Meltzer, R. S., Taylor, T. E., Schmalzle, G. M., Zheng, S., Huang, N., Wilson, A. R., Udelhofen, P. M., Comparisons of corrected daily integrated erythemal UVR from the U.S. EPA/UGA network of Brewer spectroradiometers with model and satellite data, Proceedings of SPIE, 4482, doi:10.1117/1112.452955, 2002.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sabburg, J., Rives, J. E., Meltzer, R. S., Taylor, T. E., Schmalzle, G. M., Zheng, S., Huang, N., Wilson, A. R., Udelhofen, P. M., Comparisons of corrected daily integrated erythemal UVR data from the U.S. EPA/UGA network of Brewer spectroradiometers with model and TOMS-inferred data, Journal of Geophysical Research, 107, doi:10.1029/2001JD001565, 2002.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REFERENCE MANUALS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schmalzle, G. (2005), Survival Guide for the Geodesy Lab, edited, p. 30, University of Miami, Rosenstiel School of Marine and Atmospheric Sciences Miami, FL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas, T., and Schmalzle, G. (2000), The Site Operator's Standard Operating Procedure for the Brewer Spectrophotometer, edited, NOAA.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="Schmalzle"></category><category term="Publications"></category></entry></feed>